<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[zzpxyx]]></title><description><![CDATA[zzpxyx]]></description><link>www.zzpxyx.com</link><generator>metalsmith-feed</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2016 04:39:10 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title><![CDATA[iframe Border Issue Solved]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>iOS Safari renders the iframe tag with an old-fashioned border even though I set the display property to &quot;none&quot; on that iframe tag. It took me a while to realize what was missing.</p>
<p>I was using the CSS reset technique to make browsers render my pages as consistent as possible. I was just resetting the properties margin, border, padding, and font for all the tags I used. Guess what. I forgot the iframe tag there. The border disappeared immediately after resetting the iframe tag.</p>
<p>I'm not sure the internal mechanisms though. Maybe my case was special and I didn't realize other contributing factors. Nonetheless, you could try this if you run out of ideas in dealing with similar issues.</p>
]]></description><link>posts/iframe-border-issue-solved</link><guid isPermaLink="true">posts/iframe-border-issue-solved</guid></item><item><title><![CDATA[highlight.js on CDN]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://highlightjs.org/">Highlight.js</a> is a popular library for syntax highlighting. I just figured out how to use its CDN version.</p>
<p>According to the <a href="https://highlightjs.org/download/">download instructions</a>, there is a hosted version of highlight.js. It is a prebuilt version with 23 commonly used languages. I was trying to highlight Vim script, which was not included. After searching on the Internet, I found it on <a href="https://cdnjs.com/libraries/highlight.js/">cdnjs</a>. Every supporting language was listed, so I downloaded the one for Vim script (languages/vim.min.js) immediately and started testing. It was not working because &quot;hljs&quot; was not defined.</p>
<p>It took me a while to realize the structure of those js files. The one I downloaded for Vim script was merely an addon. In other words, I still needed the file highlight.min.js as a base. After referencing both of them, Vim script highlighting finally worked.</p>
]]></description><link>posts/highlightjs-on-cdn</link><guid isPermaLink="true">posts/highlightjs-on-cdn</guid></item><item><title><![CDATA[gVim Menu Issue Solved]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Something has been wrong with my gVim's menus for quite some time. Finally, I found a workaround yesterday.</p>
<p>I'm not sure when and how the problem occurred, but one day I found that most of my gVim's menus were &quot;missing&quot;. Technically they were there, but all characters in the menu captions and items were missing. There were two strange things though. One was that the Solarized theme menu was displaying correctly. The other was that all menu items were showing the corresponding gVim commands correctly.</p>
<p>After searching around on the Internet and some trial and error, I finally found a workaround. Let's take a step back and rethink about those two strange things. Actually they were saying that only <em>some</em> characters in menu captions and items were missing. In my case, all those Chinese characters were not showing up. Now it's more clear that something might be wrong with the menu language. After manually setting the menu language to Chinese using the following line in my .vimrc, the problem was solved.</p>
<pre><code class="language-vim">set langmenu=&quot;zh_CN.UTF-8&quot;
</code></pre>
<p>I call this a workaround since I'm still not sure what caused this issue.</p>
<p>By the way, I'm using Arch Linux with Xfce. It seems that this gVim menu issue only happens in certain cases, like mine.</p>
]]></description><link>posts/gvim-menu-issue-solved</link><guid isPermaLink="true">posts/gvim-menu-issue-solved</guid></item></channel></rss>